[Music]
hi everybody
this is a film to announce the biggest
event we've ever done the rebel wisdom
festival
it's gonna be taking place at the end of
May so we wanted to take the opportunity
to explain what it is why we're doing it
and also who's gonna be there so we've
got a really exciting lineup of speakers
and all of them in some way are gonna be
talking about themes you've covered on
the channel so from the meaning crisis
to difficulty of sense making to the
information ecology and new practices
that help us see the world differently
move forward in different ways and on
that note as well we have really
top-notch lineup of facilitators so as
well as the talks which give us a kind
of scaffolding and framing it's gonna be
a lot of transformative experiences from
breadth work and circling even improv
jazz workshops so it's going to be a
whole really a festival kind of
choose-your-own-adventure festival so in
this film we're going to talk about the
whole outline of the festival introduce
the speakers play some clips from the
speakers and try and explain why we feel
that this is a kind of culmination of
the last two years of the kind of
journey of the channel and really
looking into kind of the meaning crisis
how difficult it is to make sense of the
world in an environment where a lot of
our institutions are failing to make
sense of it and then this very much
sense and understanding that we have to
really come back to our own sovereignty
our own discernment and how we the
practices to do that as well and in a
way we started this process of doing it
live last year or almost a year to the
day when the festival will be last May
at the rebel was in summit and so the
summit we capped at the Dunbar number
which was 150 people and had four
speakers we had in McGilchrist Brett
Weinstein Heather hiring and Jordan Hall
and we also broke out into groups to
have discussions about cultural topics
we find it difficult to discuss there's
kind of early exploration into how do we
make sense together
and we learned a lot from the summit I'm
basically one of the things we wanted to
do is make it bigger and better so
instead of having one day instead of
capping the numbers we put it over two
days and making it this this format
where we have a lot on offer that's why
we're calling it a fest of all there's
lots to do and you choose what you want
to do so there'll be at you know you
might want to go and see a lot of talks
you might want to do a lot of discussion
groups you might want to do a lot of
embodied practices like breath work or
circling whatever it might be and of
course you can combine all of them
together so so the point is to really
give in a way putting our money where
our mouth is we talk a lot about the
importance of doing these practices into
getting into different ways of
perceiving and so it's a it's creating a
space where we can do that where we can
actually have the option to do all of
these different things and then connect
with each other and hopefully make sense
in in a new way yeah and I'd say that
was the main learning that we had from
the summit last year was what we tried
to do with the summit was curate one
experience that all 150 people went
through and I think how big learning
from that was that paradoxically if you
give more options then you can actually
go deeper because some people really
enjoyed the the sense making together
others just wanted to kind of just see
the people up on stage which is fine
like if that's where if that's your kind
of what you want from it from a live
experience then you can do that you can
just go to the talks but with this
option because you choose your own
adventure we can actually offer slightly
deeper experiences like breadth work
like sense-making workshop and
paradoxically we realize that by by not
curating one experience for everyone
where you then have to kind of go oh is
that going to be a bit too much is that
move it too much you can actually go
deeper so I think this is this is our
learning and this is why we've decided
to go deeper bigger and with more
options for the festival this time
we also have an amazing venue in the
center of London it's much bigger than
the venue we had for the summit and it's
got four stories to it so what that
allows us to have multiple things
running at the same time there's also
three different sort of narrative tracks
running through it and the three are
meaning the meaning is a really big one
it's it's a topic we've been covering on
the channel since the beginning we've
been covering the meaning crisis this
kind of loss of connection we have in
you know our own narrative our own
historical trajectory how that plays out
in culture and there's also practices
that connect us to meaning so we're
gonna have both of those talks workshops
the next track we have is imagine
futures and imagined futures includes a
lot of the Systems Theory
and I kind of wider big-picture systems
thinking which we've also had on the
channel a lot and it's not just
big-picture thinking but it's also
exploring things like psychedelic
medicine which might start changing
paradigms it's exploring anything that's
really looking to the future and the
third track is cultural shadows and
cultural shadows runs through both those
previous tracks in some ways and what
are we not looking at when we're talking
about these things what are the things
we don't quite know how to discuss what
are the things that are our blind spots
and that's going to really run through
the entire festival and yeah I'm really
looking forward to that as well I think
it's really important to have the
discussions but also surface what we're
not talking about it's quite rare that
we have the opportunity to do that an
event so let's introduce the speakers
first up we have Rupert Sheldrake who
we've had on the channel a couple of
times and it's kind of an elder
statesman of these bigger questions
about paradigm shift like he's he's
obviously very controversial figure in
the world of science and still kind of
mainstream and isn't entirely sure what
to do with him but he's been plugging
away at this kind of where is the
scientific paradigm falling short and
where are the potential shift and he's
been involved in these conversations
since like SLN it with people like
Terence Mckenna and many of the the kind
of countercultural figures of the 70s
and 80s and he's kind of a link back to
the past and also kind of framing of
what are the lessons that maybe he and
others who were involved in these
conversations from the 70s and 80s
onwards can use can bring to shed light
on where we're at now so let's play a
short clip from Rupert because I'm the
kind of retained heretic in the world of
science I mean it's not me that
proclaims that but I'm sort of branded
as a heretic then the normal gatekeepers
and the mainstream media around the back
off when it's anything to do with me
because it's too controversial it's not
that they're afraid of the views I'm
putting forward they're afraid of people
criticizing them for allowing these
views to be expressed
you deeply feeling at all vindicated yet
or are you is that some way off yet
well the points I was making in the
science delusion ten dogmas of science
that I was talking about the changes
that have happened in science since it
came out have all gone in the direction
I was suggesting and then we have Daniel
SHM attenberger who a lot of viewers
will be familiar with from the war on
sense-making piece and some of the other
pieces that we put out on the channel
and Daniel brings a really fascinating
mix of sort of deep granular
understanding of why it's so hard to
make sense of the world why the
information ecology is so damaged
together with a really broad sweep of
systems change paradigm shift and what
is the what is the nature of the crisis
that we seem to be in at the moment it
seems to be accelerating and what might
come next we're making more and more
consequential choices with worse and
worse sense making to inform those
choices which is kind of running
increasingly fast through the woods
increasingly blind right and so I think
many of the people that you've had on
row wisdom have been in a deep inquiry
around how do we actually fix our own
sense-making and it's some of what has
brought us to have conversations with
each other because a part of how we work
with our own sense making as we
recognize the cognitive complexity of
issues that the world faces is more than
a single person can process a single
brain that can't actually hold that
cognitive complexity so it requires
collective intelligence and collective
sense making
but I can't just offload the cognitive
complexity to some Authority because I
can't trust that they're actually doing
good sense making maybe they're doing
good sense making within a very limited
context but then the application of that
outside of the context is different and
maybe there's even distortions within
their context so I have to try and find
other people that are also really
endeavoring to sense make well which
means they have to understand
and what causes failures and
sense-making
and then we have to see can we create
relationships with each other that
removed the distortion basis that is
normally there so I think I think what I
from what I have seen of rebel wisdom
this is probably the strange attractor
of what is bringing everybody to watch
it is people who are trying to make
sense of the world better themselves and
are trying to find sources of content of
other other people that have been trying
to make sense of it well which is what
I'm excited about and so those are just
some opening thoughts and yeah I look
forward to getting into why we have as
broken and information ecology as we
have and what it would take to correct
that at a at scale so what's interesting
you talk about the historical trajectory
of these kind of conversations because
the next speaker we want to talk about
is Nora Bateson and Nora Bateson is a
filmmaker a systems theorist and she
threw the Bateson Institute is carrying
on as well the work of her father who
was Gregory Bateson and Gregory Bateson
is one of the most well known
philosophers in systems theory and
cybernetics and quite a few other areas
of the 20th century so Nora has I think
a very interesting take on systems
change which she actually refers to as
systems learning so moving beyond seeing
it from a kind of engineering mode as a
fixed system to seeing it as a very
alive system so I'll just play a we'll
play a clip from Nora now there's plenty
of great information you can get with
reductionist
process but you can't understand how the
vitality of a living system is actually
shifting and moving and if it's not
shifting and moving it's not alive
anymore so we have a we have a conundrum
there of how we're going to think about
what information is when so much of what
has been developed in terms of what we
think of as authorized information
aesthetic and what we need to understand
and respond to is complex and alive so
Nora is also going to be running
something called
warm day to lab which is very much based
around the idea that information can't
be taken out of its context we have to
look at every piece of information as
relationally connected to other pieces
of information the workshops are all
about how do we start perceiving in that
way and how do we start solving problems
using that methodology then we have one
of our favorite people John Vevey key
who many of you will know from his
awakening from the meaning crisis series
which made him a kind of little cult
figure online and we've had him on the
channel a number of times and in this he
will be speaking directly to the meaning
crisis what is the meaning crisis what
are the deep stories of Western culture
that has led us to the point where we're
at now
and where might we go next and in
addition to the talk that he's going to
be giving he's also going to be leading
a workshop with Peter Limburg who you
might know from culture war 2.0 about
dialogue oz dialogue oz being a live
conversation between more than one
person how do we come to truth together
what is the process of arriving at
wisdom all of these deep questions so
we're really excited about what he's
going to bring the problem that's
happened for us is that the worldview
within which our wisdom traditions arose
has been significantly undermined for a
host of very interconnected and complex
historical reasons that have to do with
things like the Protestant Reformation
the emergence of the scientific
worldview the movements in the
separation of philosophy from a
transformative set of practices unlike
what it was in the ancient world with
Socrates or Plato we get the loss of
wisdom institutions like the monastic
tradition within the West is destroyed
because of the Protestant Reformation so
for a whole host of historical reasons
we have a worldview in which we as
meaning makers don't belong and then we
also and that worldview also doesn't
tell it tells us how to get information
and even if right even if you if you
want to give sort of a broad reading
side to tell us how to get knowledge but
it really doesn't tell us how to
cultivate wisdom and that leads on to
our next speakers Gail Bradbrook so a
lot of the stuff daniel trachtenberg
talking about this this sense of our
current system reaching a point where
it's not really working anymore there's
a lot of groups around the world who are
in some way responding to that and one
of the most successful recently and
largest has been extinction rebellion
and Gael is one of the founders of
extinction rebellion so it's interesting
to get a take on how is this actually
playing out practically and how are
people organizing and mobilizing around
issues like this so on that subject of
the way new paradigms are starting to
come up in society in lots of different
areas we have dr. Rosalind Watts who's
the clinical lead at Imperial on the
psilocybin for depression trial and has
been working in that area for a number
of years and will be talking about how
this new paradigm of psychedelic
medicine starts to kind of turn on its
head the the previous paradigm we've had
around medicine and what does it
actually mean where does actually what
do we need to know about that is there a
tension between because a lot of time
with with the medical model the idea is
you take a pill and it has this effect
on you like it's a very kind of material
idea or a very mechanistic assumption it
feels that there's something very
different going on with psychedelics do
you think there's a there's a weird
tension I think it's a very good tension
because I think the tension that is
there has the power to really transforms
our system of care I think what
psychedelics bring about is this
absolute paradigm shift in that you
can't use psychedelics in that way
psychedelics will never be able to
safely be put into a kind of conveyor
belt system of care they will radically
transform any system of care they're
brought into you because in order to do
them safely you need all the things I
think we're important for therapeutic
changes to happen so you absolutely
cannot give a psychedelic substance to
someone without proper trust and that
means proper trust that they have for
themselves for the therapist for silat
the psilocybin substance like proper
proper trust and that doesn't get
developed overnight so staying on the
theme of new paradigms we have Jules
Evans philosopher who's been on the
channel a few times he actually wrote a
really fascinating piece called dude
where's my paradigm shift kind of saying
there's been this conversation since at
least the 1960s and probably earlier
than s about all we're on the kind of
fraught
the edge of something new and why is
that not happened and is it kind of very
naive to even think about things in that
way and talk about things in that way
very possibly it could be a piece for
the cultural shadows to kind of talk
about is this whole idea kind of just
naive wishful thinking but Jules is a
really really fascinating thinker
because he very deeply learned in into
the various different types of
philosophy kind of very much was very
involved in the stoic mute movement for
a long time and then got a sense that it
was missing something that stoicism was
missing the sort of deep lived
transformational side of things I was
interested in a history of ecstatic
experiences and I feel like Western
culture rather marginalized and
pathologized ecstasy starting from
around the Reformation as in by
pathologized I mean it got redefined as
a mental illness so in the 17th and 18th
centuries rationalist materialist
thinkers like Thomas Hobbes would say
ecstasy is enthusiasm delusion you're
just letting yourself be carried away
with your imagination in the 19th
century psychiatrists like jean-martin
charcot said ecstasy is just hysteria a
symptom of a brain disorder all the
ecstatics of yesteryear he said from
Joan of Arc to Socrates to Mohammed are
actually suffering from brain disorders
20th century psychiatry said something
similar you know if you say I'm spirits
are talking to me I'm connected to the
universe that's actually just psychosis
so that's the main story I think and as
a result of that there's a taboo around
ecstasy this is something that Stan Grof
talks really well about yeah Stan and
Stan Grof is very important in this in
this kind of thing so psychiatry
pathologized ecstasy so we still have
these experiences because they're
naturally occurring but we don't talk
about them because we don't look
ridiculous or stupid or mad so one of
the things we've been exploring on the
channel as well as collective
intelligence this idea of us being more
than the sum of our parts when we come
together to you know
solve a problem or make sense of the
world together and there's a metaphor
that keeps coming up over and over again
which is jazz so a jazz ensemble is is
often held up as a you know kind of the
perfect collective intelligence idea
metaphor and there's probably no bigger
expert on that than Greg Thomas who's
our next speaker and Greg runs with his
wife jewel the jazz leadership project
and so he's really excellent at
explaining taking the theory of
collective intelligence and then mapping
against this jazz metaphor that's why
when I saw that conversation in other
work on rebel wisdom it's exciting
because you have folks that are
listening deeply which is another very
important practice in jazz that we
should discuss but they're coming forth
with inflammation and perspectives
that's deeply informed so when jazz
artists are playing together great jazz
artists they're doing so in a way where
they're communicating they're having a
conversation they're respecting the
individuality and leadership potential
we call that shared leadership of the
others as they engage in the moment so
say the saxophone is solos first the
saxophone this is the lead during that
moment everyone is supporting him or her
same with the trumpet and then the
rhythm section they also get a chance to
solo or improvise so that's one of the
models of shared leadership and that's
the same thing that happens in
conversations among friends particularly
deeply informed friends so Greg and his
wife jewel are also going to be running
a jazz leadership project workshop to
kind of give give us all a lived
experience of these ideas so then we
have Alex Evans who's been on the
channel talking about his collective
psychology project but before that in
2017 he wrote a really influential book
called the myth gap and Alex's
background is in policymaking he was a
government adviser for many years and
what he noticed was that the
conversation was very very narrow it was
all about statistics and very dry and he
was sort of sensing there's something
really missing here and what's missing
is this sense of
the stories that actually can move
people and put be genuinely sort of
transformational what-what would and the
myth gap was all about this like well
religions have got this and there seems
to be a gap where religion normally goes
and that's having such a big kind of
sweeping impact on us as as people at
their best religions have really
performed this role of kind of putting
tools for agency out there into the
world and in terms of belonging of
course religions have been all about
creating congregational spaces where
people feel like they can belong in
spite of their differences in spite of
their shortcomings so that's if you like
a separate set of things that religions
have historically done for us but you
know as with myth it's something that
turns out to be incredibly important for
our collective psychological health and
now we're looking around for you know
how to fill that gap so then we have
Peter Limburg who we recently featured
on the channel with the culture war 2.0
piece and that's been a really
influential piece in this sort of wider
sense making conversation I think the
the framing of memetic tribes the idea
of hermetic mediation and some of the
other concepts that were put forward in
that piece I've had a really Illustrated
a lot of what's going on from a sort of
broader cultural perspective one aspect
about mimetic tribes is this the sense
that they're disembodied because they're
exercising this sense of tribalism
around a certain idea a certain ideology
a certain mean Plex
but not really meeting or hearing in
person and there's a an egoic aspect to
this there there's their ego likely
attached to the ideas that they're are
fighting with where I think what rebel
wisdom is gesturing towards and various
different people in a sense making web
is trying to create an embodied tribe
where people actually get together in
person and explore ideas and also Peter
will be running a workshop around
mimetic tribes and culture war 2.0 and
as well as the speakers we have some
amazing facilitators running everything
from circling workshops through the
breathwork
transformative tech
discussion and inquiry groups and even
improv and of course jazz and last but
not least there will be a big party as
well so we're still adding facilitators
and speakers so keep watching the
website to be updated about that and a
reminder of the date is the 30th and
31st of May so there's a lot going on of
the festival there's a lot of options to
choose from and it's very much a
pick-your-own adventure experience we
also have some surprises planned to make
it more of an immersive experience which
we won't go into now and if you want to
learn more about it just visit the
website you can read in more detail
who's there what the format is gonna be
in what to expect and we hope to see you
there like to be heard I sing it I sing
this whole thing that'd be weird
welcome to rebel wisdom first of all
we've done a summer tan it was good but
this will be better that's pretty much
it
[Music]